Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太｡
栄光の日 生まれの➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
ひびと
弟･日々人は 日本人初の
ムーンウォーカーとなった＞
＜その 遥か後ろから
月を目指し始めた 兄･六太は➡
Older brother Mutta continues on his long quest to the moon,
日々人との約束を胸に
海底での訓練を終え➡
as he trains at the bottom of the ocean, to fulfill his promise to Hibito.
ケンジや新田と共に ミｯシｮンへの
アサインを待っている＞
Kenji, Nitta, and Mutta now wait to be assigned to missions.
＜一方 月面での事故の影響で
パニｯク障害となった日々人は➡
Meanwhile, Hibito struggles to recover from the panic disorder
宇宙飛行士として復帰すべく
もがき苦しんでいる＞
that's afflicted him since a lunar accident, to return to active duty.
＜しかし そのことを
六太は まだ知らない＞
However, Mutta still does not know the truth.
"Olga Grows Up," volume 2.
なんば
(南波日々人)《オリガ１１歳
その成長記録》
Yes, yes! Wonderful, Olga!
[PC](教師)そうそう いいわよ
オリガ｡脚を高くあげて➡
Keep your leg high.
上手になってきた｡イリーナ
腕を もっと伸ばすように➡
You're improving!
Irina, extend your arm all the way, with grace.
軽やかに…そぉ～いいわ｡
エカテリーナ➡
Yes, that's wonderful!
Catherine, head up high.
顔上げて！目線を前に向ける！
Keep your eyes forward.
[PC](オリガ)あっ！
Olga!
[PC](生徒)オリガ！先生！
Coach, look at Olga!
[PC]オリガが…｡
[PC]大丈夫？オリガ｡
Are you okay, Olga?
[PC](ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)どうした オリガ｡
大丈夫か？
What's wrong, Olga?
Are you all right?
[PC](オリガ)い…痛い｡
[PC](教師)見せてみなさい｡➡
I-It hurts...
Let me take a look.
ねんざ
捻挫したようね｡
[PC]変に ひねりました｡
It looks sprained...
I landed on it funny...
[PC](教師)
無理に立たないように｡病院に
行く準備を いたしましょう｡
Don't try to stand up.
Let's get ready to take you to the hospital.
[PC](ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)先生 私はおもてに
車をまわしてきます｡
Coach, I'll bring the car around.
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#87 To the Place Where I Belong
《オリガは 右足首を捻挫した｡
おそらく １ヵ月ほどで➡
Olga sprained her right ankle.
She would only need a month to recover.
治る程度のものだろうけど｡
静かにストレスを溜めていた➡
But it was more than enough to make a stressed-out eleven-year-old girl throw in the towel...
１１の少女が 何かをやめて
しまうには 充分な出来事だった》
Florida
ふうか
(風佳)えいっ！
ママ 早く早く！
Hurry up, Mommy!
(ユキ)はいはい｡風佳ったら
はしゃいじゃって！
Right, right.
You're too excited, Fuuka.
(風佳)だって…｡
(ケンジ)風佳！➡
That's 'cause...
Fuuka!
お～い！
あ～パパ！
Hey!
Ah, Daddy!
お～！ハハハ！
Daddy!
よく来たな 風佳｡
Thanks for coming to see me, Fuuka.
Sure, I didn't mind riding the bus to visit you.
パパに会えるから
バス 全然いやじゃなかったよ｡➡
Oh, Mu...
あっ ムックー！
(南波六太)よぉ フーちゃん！
Yo, Fu.
Nitta, could you also grill these?
にった
(ユキ)新田さん こっちのも
もう焼いちゃって下さい｡
(新田)了解です｡
(ユキ)ケンちゃん それが
よく混ざったら➡
Got it.
Ken, once you're done mixing that, could you stuff these peppers for me?
こっちのピーマンに
詰めてくれる？程よくね｡
(ケンジ)うん わかった｡
Sure.
Hey, hey, Mu...
(風佳)ねえねえ ムックー｡
What's up?
(風佳)何か面白いこと言って｡
お…面白いこと？
Say something funny.
S-Something funny?
よぉし｡じゃあ フーちゃんに
ダジャレというものを➡
Uh-huh.
Okay!
Then I'll teach you some puns.
教えてあげよう｡
ダジャレ？
Puns?
Yep, puns!
そう ダジャレ｡
じゃあ まず基本を｡
Let's start with a basic one.
ウッホンッ！
ふとんが ふっ飛んだ｡
A patient patient!
あ～ とかね…｡
俺んちで オレンジ食う？
Or how about...
An Orange County orange?
Hmm?
アハハー…｡
You're supposed to laugh.
とかね…｡
Look at this...
ほら こうすれば
アルミ缶の上にあるミカン だよ｡
An orange can sit on a can.
There... Get it?
わかる～？
(ユキ)このまな板 何か
よく すべるんだけど｡
When no one laughs, you look silly.
(ケンジ)大丈夫？
Huh? That's fine.
まだあるけど…聞く？
(風佳)う～ん よくわかんない！
I have more... Interested?
Dunno!
ハハ…南波のやつ
５歳児相手に すべってやがる｡
Nanba can't even make a five-year-old laugh.
ウフフ…｡
じゃあ…じゃあ 今度フーちゃんが
何か面白いこと言ってみてよ｡
Th-Then, why don't you say something funny?
例えば ほら ここに
コロネがあるから➡
For example... See this chocolate cornet?
コロネで何か言ってみて｡
Say something funny about it.
Don't forget the cornet... Clever.
《コロネが焼ける頃ね｡
あっ 上手い！》
あっ コロネがふっ飛んだ！
Oh! A patient cornet!
あとね…アルミ缶の上にある
ミカンの上に あるミカン！
And then,
an orange can sit on an orange can...
sit on a can!
おぉ～…まいりました｡
You win...
僕らの行く先は
どうなってるんだろうね？
I wonder where we'll be headed...
ニーモ
ＮＥＥＭＯが終わって
３日くらいじゃ まだ決まらないか｡
NEEMO training only ended three days ago, so they probably haven't decided yet.
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡは 今後の方針を
なかなか教えてくれないからな｡➡
NASA doesn't like to discuss future plans,
決まってたとしても｡
even when they've already decided...
おっ うん…うめぇ｡
Yum...
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)月を逃した宇宙飛行士は
そのあと どうなるのか➡
What happens to astronauts who miss this chance to go to the moon?
全く情報が おりてこないから
不安にもなるよね｡
There's no information, so all we can do is worry.
If they would tell us our options, we could prepare for the next step.
言ってくれれば そこに向かって
覚悟を決めるのにな｡
(風佳)キャハハ！無理無理
倒れちゃうよ！
That won't work... It'll fall down!
何の何の！アルミ缶の上に
あるミカンの上にある➡
I wouldn't say that!
A can can sit on an orange can sit on an orange can sit on a...
ミカンの上に ある…｡
ミカン！
Can!
あ～…ハハッ！
That's great!
すごいすごい！アハハ！
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)じゃあ 始めようか
準備はいいかい？ヒビト｡
Let's get started, then.
Are you ready, Hibito?
ああ｡始めよう｡
Yeah,
let's do this.
ヘルメットを｡
ありがとう｡
Here's your helmet.
Thanks.
If you can walk fifteen meters and wear the pressure suit for forty minutes,
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)１５メｰトル歩いて４０分間
よあつふく
その与圧服姿で➡
過ごせたら
テン
レベル１０は クリアだ｡
you'll pass Level 10.
[PC](ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)ウホッ！え～ 今ここは
モスクワ市立病院｡➡
This is the Moscow City Hospital.
ご覧の通り オリガは
脚をケガしてしまいました｡➡
As you can see, Olga has injured her leg.
捻挫です｡痛いか？オリガ｡
She sprained it.
Does it hurt, Olga?
[PC]痛い！ウッ！
It hurts...
[PC](ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)代われるものなら
代わってやりたいけどな｡
I wish I could take your place.
Then do it.
[PC](ｵﾘｶﾞ)じゃあ代わって｡
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)
え～ ケガから５日目｡
バレエが出来なくなった➡
So, it's been five days since the injury.
Now that she can't practice ballet, what's Olga up to?
オリガが どうなったか…｡
ご覧ください｡➡
Let's take a look.
だらけてま～す！兄と一緒に｡
She's being lazy! And her big brother has joined her!
[PC](兄)よっと！ハハ…
オリガ 下手すぎ｡
You really suck, Olga.
[PC]いいの！ちょっと お母さんまで
カメラやめてよね｡
Don't care.
Hey... Mom, don't start filming everything like Dad.
[PC]ヘヘッ｡
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)今日から お父さん
長期訓練なの｡
Your father will be away to train for a while.
Wow, this place is a total mess!
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)わぁ～！何
この散らかりよう！➡
Can't you clean up your room, Olga?
ちょっとは片付けなさい オリガ｡
[PC]今から やるとこなの｡
I was about to do that.
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)
じゃ～ん！これ見てオリガ｡
ソーニャ･カルビナ主演の➡
Ta-dah! Look at this, Olga...
I have a ticket to Sonia Karabina's ballet performance!
バレエコンクールの
チケットで～す！
[PC]うん…｡
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)あれ 行かないの？
ｿｰﾆｬ好きなんでしょ｡
Oh? Don't you want to go?
Aren't you a fan?
[PC]う～ん…何か しばらく
バレエ以外のことしたい｡
I feel like spending time on something that isn't ballet.
《厳しいバレエの世界に
浸かりっぱなしだった➡
An eleven-year-old girl, crumbling under the pressure of the ballet,
１１歳の少女の目には
バレエ以外のものは何でも➡
found everything else to be better.
魅惑的に映ったのかもしれない｡
脚のケガは 痛みとともに➡
Her injury was painful,
彼女に解放感を与えてしまった》
but it also set her free...
[PC](ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)なんだオリガ もう
踊りは やめたのか？➡
What's this, Olga?
Are you going to quit dancing?
脚も治って ずいぶん経つだろう｡
Your leg finished healing a while ago.
[PC]う～ん…だって 何だかまた
ケガすんの やだし➡
Well, I don't want to get injured again.
いいの 別に｡
Don't feel like bothering.
いつまで ふててんだよ｡
ほんとは踊りたいくせに｡
How long does she keep this up...
I know she really wants to dance.
わっ！もう１２歳!?
Huh?! She's already twelve?
After her injury, the eleven-year-old Olga never danced again.
《結局 １１のオリガは
ケガ以降 一度も踊らなかった》
一度やめてたのか…踊ること｡
She quit dancing for some time...
《オリガがまた 踊りを始めた
きっかけは 何だったのか？》
Why did she start to dance again?
Then...
《それは…１２のオリガを
見て わかった》
I saw the twelve-year-old Olga, and I knew why.
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)ほらオリガ
お父さん来たわよ｡
Look, Olga... There's your dad.
[PC]うん｡
[PC]あ…おとう…さん｡
D-Dad...
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)さあ いよいよ
打ち上げで～す！➡
It's finally time for the launch!
我らがお父さんは まもなく
宇宙に向かいます｡➡
Dad is about to go to space.
オリガ 真剣に見てます｡
Olga's watching closely.
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)
打ち上げ成功！やった～!!
The launch is a success! Hurray!
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)
お父さん 行っちゃったねぇ
オリガ｡あっという間…｡
Dad's on his way to space, Olga.
It happened so fast.
[PC]お父さん…スゴイ!!
Dad's amazing!
[PC](ﾃﾚﾋﾞ:ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)
ああ～そうだ
アイエスエス
今度ＩＳＳへ来たら➡
Oh, yes...
There's something I wanted to try on the ISS.
やろうと思ってたことがあるんだ｡
[PC](ﾐﾊｲﾙ)何だろ？
What's that?
[PC](ﾃﾚﾋﾞ:ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)
娘のオリガが
見ててくれるといいが…｡➡
I hope that my daughter, Olga, is watching.
いくぞ～！父の無重力バレエ｡➡
This is your father performing zero-gravity ballet!
よ～っ！ほ～ら
見てるか？オリガ！➡
Look!
Are you watching, Olga?
ハハハハ！ハハハ…｡
[PC]あはっ！
[PC](ﾃﾚﾋﾞ:ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)
誰かが止めてくれないと➡
I won't stop spinning until someone stops me!
回り続けるんだ これは｡ハハハ…｡
[PC]バカだね…お父さん｡
Dad's so silly.
[PC](ﾃﾚﾋﾞ:ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)
楽しいぞ～ガハハハ！
This is fun...
[PC]んっ？
《この時だ》
This is it.
《次のシーンでは 部屋の中で
踊り出すオリガがいた》
The next scene was Olga in the room, spontaneously starting to dance.
[PC]ハハッ アハハハ！
[PC](ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)ごらんくださ～い｡➡
Look at this!
ウチの娘です｡踊ってま～す｡
This is our daughter! She's dancing!
はっはは いいぞ！
そうだ オリガ！踊れ！
Way to go!
That's more like it, Olga... Dance!
Don't ever stop dancing.
《もっと…もっと踊ってくれ！》
Twelve-year-old Olga...
《１２のオリガは
再びバレエをはじめた》
returned to ballet.
《再び…》
She returned...
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)やった～!!
You did it!
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)よし！
(ｵﾘﾋﾞｱ)１５メートル歩行 クリア｡
All right!
You made it fifteen meters.
ふっ…ははっ！
んっ はぁ～｡今なら この格好で
踊るのだって出来そうだ｡
I think I'm ready to start dancing in this suit.
(アポ)ヘッヘッヘッへッ｡
早く早く～｡
Quick!
《先客か…》
Someone else was here?
あずま
(吾妻)よお お前もか…日々人｡
Yo.
You decided to drop by, too, Hibito?
マジだって｡見たんだよ オレ｡➡
I'm not lying...
I saw him walk into the mock-up control room in the NBL.
エヌビーエル
ＮＢＬのモックアップ保管室に
入っていった｡
The mock-up control room?
(同僚)モックアップ保管室？
Didn't someone say he's been giving Japanese lessons?
(同僚)日本語教室やってるって
話じゃなかった？
保管室でやるこっちゃねえな｡
He wouldn't give lessons in the control room...
だから 日本語なんて
やってないってことだ｡
Then he isn't teaching them Japanese.
So what are they doing?
じゃあ 何やってんだ？
訓練用モックアップの
点検とか？
Is it some kind of training?
おい｡
Hey... Speak of the devil, it's Hibito.
噂をすればヒビトだ｡
Hibito! Haven't seen you around in a while...
(同僚)ヒビト～久しぶりだな～｡➡
Have you been doing any training?
最近 全く
訓練してね～んじゃねぇか？
これから始まるんだよ｡
I'm gonna start soon.
日本語の訓練なら
オレらも交ぜてくれよ｡
If you're offering Japanese training, invite us.
保管室以外で頼むぜ｡
プハッ｡
But don't use the control room.
悪いね
日本語教室は昨日で終わったよ｡
Sorry, but Japanese lessons ended yesterday.
じゃ 急いでるから またね｡
Well, I'm in a hurry, so later... Sayonara!
サヨナ～ラ～｡
おいっ｡
Huh?
Hey!
Congrats, Hibito!
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)⦅おめでとう ヒビト～｡➡
You wore the pressure suit for forty-five minutes.
与圧服で４０分維持
レベル１０クリアだよ～！⦆
You've cleared Level 10!
(ｵﾘﾋﾞｱ)⦅おめでとう ヒビト⦆
Congratulations, Hibito.
⦅ふう…ありがとう ありがとう⦆
Thanks...
Thanks.
⦅私の方がドキドキしたわ⦆
I was more nervous about it than you.
⦅これで 僕らに手伝える訓練は
全てクリアだ｡➡
That means you've cleared all the training that we can help with...
You did a good job, Hibito!
よくやったよヒビト｡➡
残るは船外宇宙服だけど…
さすがに あれを➡
The last thing is the EVA suit.
But we can't grab one to use for personal reasons...
極秘で持ち出すのは
不可能なわけで…⦆
⦅わかってるよ｡
ありがとう ローリー｡➡
I know.
Thanks, Lowry.
All that's left is to talk to the chief, and ask him to put me to the test.
あとは直接 室長にかけ合って
その目で見てもらうしかない⦆
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)⦅きっと うまくいくよ！⦆
I know you can do it!
I know I can do it.
《きっと…うまくいく》
室長 お願いがあります｡
Chief, I have a request.
俺に もう一度
チャンスをください｡
Please give me one more chance.
宇宙飛行士に戻る準備が
できました｡
I'm ready to return to being an astronaut.
I've been waiting for you.
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)待っていたよ｡
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)⦅待っていたよ⦆
I've been waiting for you.
《俺は…戻りたいんだ》
I want to return.
《おさえきれずに踊りだした
オリガみたいに…》
The same way Olga couldn't stop herself from dancing.
《俺もあんな風に…➡
I want to return...
自分の場所へ戻りたい》
To the place where I belong!
(アポ)ワンワン！ワンワンワン！
ワンワン！ワンワンワン！
ワン！ワンワンワン…｡
ん～今日は午後からなんだ アポ｡
I don't have anything until this afternoon, Apo...
クィ～ン｡
あぁ…何だよ 散歩の要求か｡
ヘッヘッヘッへッ｡
Wh-What is it? You want me to walk you?
ん～あっ そうか｡
Oh...
今日は…｡
Today's...
アポ～おいで｡
Apo, shake.
《先客か…こんな朝から》
Someone else was here? So early?
《まぁ…命日だもんな》
Well, it is the anniversary...
《ブライアン
バトラー室長に頼んで➡
Brian, I asked Chief Butler
俺が宇宙飛行士に戻るための
試験を➡
to let me take a test, so I can return to being an astronaut.
やってもらうことになったよ》
《気合は十分だけど それでも
まだ…怖いよ ブライアン》
I'm fired up, but on the inside...
I'm still scared, Brian.
《ＮＡＳＡの上官達の見てる前で
もし発作が出てしまったら➡
If I have an attack while the NASA directors are watching,
フリダシに戻るどころじゃ
済まない》
it'll only get worse.
《多分 俺はもう…二度と宇宙へは
行かせてもらえないだろうな》
I'm sure they'd never let me go back to space...
《あんたなら
どうする ブライアン》
What would you do, Brian?
Yo.
(吾妻)よお お前もか…日々人｡
You decided to drop by, too, Hibito?
吾妻さん｡
Azuma...
いや～帰ってきたね～
ヒューストン｡
Yeah, we've returned to Houston.
ただいま｡
We're back.
You guys are late!
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)遅いわよ あんたら！➡
だいたい今日みたいな寒い日に
わざわざ出迎えに行かせる➡
I have no idea why my boss made me pick you up on such a cold day,
上司もどうかと思うけど
あんたらがビシッと➡
but if you'd showed up on time,
予定の時刻に着いてりゃ
パッパと用件伝えて 私は今頃➡
I'd already be done with my spiel, and I'd be drinking coffee and eating donuts in my office, while relaxing...
オフィスでコーヒーと
ドーナツでも食べながら➡
まったり過ごしてたってのにねえ｡
Do you know how long I was waiting?
一体 どんだけ待ったと
思ってんのよ！➡
I was here long enough to write an entire novel in my mind!
頭の中で短編小説が
１本できそうだったわよ！➡
If I make my authorial debut, you're required to buy my books!
もし私が作家デビューしたら
あんたらが まず本買いなさいよ！
Ten copies each... No, a hundred!
１冊と言わず１０冊 いや100冊!!
W-We're back...
《か…帰ってきたな～》
And so, you three are supposed to run over to the chief's office, one at a time.
というわけだから
あんたら３人とも➡
今すぐ１人ずつ
ダッシュで室長室に行きなさい｡
えっ！室長室？
Eh? The chief's office?
That's right.
そうよ｡
バトラー室長が 呼んでるわ｡
Chief Butler wants to see you.
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#88 Pretty Dog
If I fail this test, I'll never make it back to space.
＜復帰試験に失敗したら
二度と宇宙へ行けない＞
＜こんなとき あんただったら
どうする？ブライアン＞
What would you do in this situation, Brian?
You have another big brother to turn to.
(吾妻)＜お前には もう一人
兄貴がいるだろう＞
Next time on Space Brothers:
"Pretty Dog"
＜ムッちゃん｡今日は話すわ＞
Mu, I have something to tell you.